<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short reply to the postscript, &amp;c. of H.S. Shewing his many falsities in matters of fact; the impertinencies of his promised answers to some physicians that have written against the apothecaries: his conspiracy with apothecaries to defame them, the R.S. and many learned men of our nation. Made by Christopher Merrett Dr. of physic and fellow of the college of physicians.</title>
            <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833075</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833075</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1782:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short reply to the postscript, &amp;c. of H.S. Shewing his many falsities in matters of fact; the impertinencies of his promised answers to some physicians that have written against the apothecaries: his conspiracy with apothecaries to defame them, the R.S. and many learned men of our nation. Made by Christopher Merrett Dr. of physic and fellow of the college of physicians.</title>
                  <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.R. for James Allestry, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to a postscript of: Stubbs, Henry.  Campanella revived.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stubbe, Henry, 1632-1676. --  Campanella revived --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Royal Society (Great Britain) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37550:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37550:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT REPLY TO THE Poſtſcript, &amp;c. of <hi>H. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing his many Falſities in matters of Fact; the impertinencies of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Anſwers to ſome Phyſicians that have written againſt the Apothecaries: his conſpiracy with Apothecaries to defame them, the <hi>R. S.</hi> and many Learned men of our Nation.</p>
            <p>Made by <hi>Chriſtopher Merrett</hi> Dr. of <hi>Phyſic</hi> and Fellow of the College of <hi>Phyſicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>James Alleſtry,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37550:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37550:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here coming to my hands a Pamphlet intituled <hi>Campanella revived;</hi> with a Poſtſcript concerning the quarrel depending betwixt <hi>H. S.</hi> and <hi>Dr Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> and wondring there ſhould be a quarrel depending betwixt my ſelf, and any other perſon, having never wrote, or ſaid any thing againſt any ſingle perſon, I ſoon run over his Epiſtle to the Reader, and found <hi>Henry Stubbs</hi> ſubſcribed to it, who in other Papers ſtiles himſelf a <hi>Phyſician</hi> at <hi>Warwick.</hi> A perſon whom I never ſaw, but have ſeen Books of his writing againſt very learned and worthy perſons, and whoſe beſt parts have been imploied in wrangling with men far better then himſelf, and therefore amongſt all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons his Pen is no ſlander; Wherefore my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution was not to return any anſwer at all. But up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſecond thoughts, and by the advice of ſome other learned Friends and Colleagues I ſoon diſpatched theſe Papers, which had come abroad three weeks ago, had our Preſſes bin at leaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37550:3"/>Before I come to ſpeak particularly to his Poſtſcript, I ſhall mention ſeveral falſities and untruths delivered in this Pamphlet againſt <hi>the R. S. and my ſelf,</hi> and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly ſhall offer my reaſons to impartial men to make it plain, that <hi>the Apothecaries are the Authors, Fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or adjutors in it.</hi> Thirdly I ſhall detect their cunning contrivances, in defending themſelves from having <hi>their Books (eſpecially this Pamphlet) made Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Falſities in matter of Fact; in his preface to the reader he ſaith <hi>the Royal Society would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated the Colledge of Phiſicians into their Society, but that the prudent and grave did decline,</hi> a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dreamt on; 'tis true Mr. <hi>Colwell</hi> my Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a very noble Benefactor to the <hi>R. S.</hi> and my ſelf, conſidering the College of Phyſitians was conſumed by Fire, and that the R. S. alſo wanted a convenience for their meetings, we both judged it meet to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to each Society, that a common place of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing might be erected at the common charges of them both; which deſign none of our College but judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be much for their advantage, and moſt of the Council of the R. S. approved at firſt, but upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts rejected; urging that both the name of the place and honour would be wholy the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and therefore never endeavoured to incorporate the Phyſicians into their Society, a thing very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous and abſur'd in it ſelf; becauſe <hi>his Majeſty</hi> had eſtabliſhed them as two Corporations with diſtinct Lawes and Government. When this conjunction of purſes onely was firſt propoſed at a College meeting, one onely prudent and grave perſon did not decline (as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37550:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Mr. <hi>Stubs</hi> ſaith) but thought fit, we ſhould conſider on it, but ſince upon more mature deliberation the ſame prudent perſon would have brought it on again.</p>
            <p>A ſecond falſity is, <hi>that the R. S. promoted the Anti-College of Pſeudo-Chymiſts incouraging Odowde and his adherents in oppoſition to the Phyſicians.</hi> This I confeſs is news to Phyſicians here who are ſure never any thing was propoſed, or indeavoured by the Society to that purpoſe. Who have been obſervant enough of whatſoever they have ſeemed at leaſt to intrench on our Faculty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>H. S.</hi> hath four falſities complicated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in theſe words. <q>
                  <hi>Nor would I have any man to believe that there are ſo many eminent Phyſicians of the R. S., for neither is the number of thoſe admitted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable: few of note but have deſerted it again, the reſt approve not of it, ſo that all they talk of will not amount to three underſtanding Perſons.</hi>
               </q> To which I reply that in the Liſt of the laſt year 1669, I find 34 Phyſicians to be members of the R. S. and that the number of them is conſiderable, will appear by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving yearly four or five or more of the Council, the whole number amounting but to 21. And that none of the Phyſicians have deſerted them is manifeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not ſignified in writing their mind to the Preſident as their ſtatutes require. But that thoſe that remain approve not of it is moſt falſe, and will be ſo, 'till <hi>the Phyſicians find them invadors of their Faculty, prejudicial to the Arts, Church, or State,</hi> and if there be but two underſtanding Phyſicians (as you deny there are more.) You may be ſure the reſt of the Faculty perſwaded by the reaſons of theſe two and their own intereſt will ſoon leave them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37550:4"/>Fourthly, In the Poſcript <hi>H. S.</hi> affirms, <hi>That all the books written on that ſubject (the Apothecaries) proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them, (the Royal Society.)</hi> I perceive Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> hath not read all Books (a great accuſation againſt the R. S. all along his papers) or elſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly prevaricates, I am ſure <hi>Bartholinus</hi> who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Latin two treatiſes, written by two ſeveral Phyſicians, <hi>intituled the frauds and abuſes of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries,</hi> nor Dr. <hi>Hodges</hi> nor Dr. <hi>Manwaring.</hi> nor a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late writer (who is <hi>Anonymus</hi>) were ever members of the <hi>R. S.</hi> And for my ſelf I do affirm that not one member <hi>of the R. S. but thoſe that were of the College of Phyſitians alſo,</hi> joyned with ſome others that were never of <hi>the R. S.</hi> did know any thing concerning the Publication of my View; ſo far are they from being principal incendiaries in this affair, <hi>as H. S. moſt falſely alledgeth they were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, He affirms, that <hi>there wanted not ſome of them (the R. S.) who purpoſed to erect a Laboratory, and Shop whence all ſhould be furniſhed cheaper and better than now, as to general Medicines,</hi> &amp;c. This alſo is wholy falſe, and will be believed ſo till he names the perſons that thus act.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>H. S.</hi> makes <hi>me confeſs that this quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Phyſicians and Apothecaries was of no longer continuance than that of the R. S.</hi> Whereas in my View <hi>p.</hi> 21. I affirm the Apothecaries have continually tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the College, troubled them at the Council board, Parliaments, &amp;c. and that <hi>Anno</hi> 1639. a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> was granted againſt them, beſides I now ſay this open Conteſt had its riſe ſome years before, and not long after their Corporation was erected in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37550:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>15th year of K. James,</hi> by the procurement of ſome of our College, and whoſoever ſhall read over our Annals (as I have done twice) will find the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> to have been conſtant underminers and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to our Profeſſion and Corporation.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, His <hi>Poſtcript falſely affirms that I made him the Author of</hi> Lex Talionis. For thus he begins his Poſtſcript. <hi>Sir, the news you writ me about Dr. Merrett did at firſt a little ſurprize me, and had I not during this laſt year been accuſtomed to the puny ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of the Virtuoſi, I ſhould have wondered much to underſtand that I was intituled to the</hi> Lex Talionis, <hi>or that Apology for Apothecaries to practice Phyſick. But the Comedians finding their anger inſignificant againſt me, by reaſon the advantages their ignorance had given me over them; have aſcribed unto me a Book which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of an eaſie reply, and which interferes with the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Phyſitians, that ſo they might ſeem to baffle, and inodiate me at once in the judgment of that profeſſion for which I ſeemed concerned: I cannot make any defence not having ſeen his Book.</hi> Whereupon obſerve another falſe accuſation of the <hi>R. S.</hi> in his making them Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of it; whereas none of them before the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſaw line of it: Secondly what honeſt and fair intelligence <hi>this Phyſician at Warwick</hi> hath, for in that Book I clearly abſolve him of being the Author of it, for in page the firſt I onely ſay that I was informed, (and ſay ſo ſtill) that the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> gave out Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> was the Author of <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> and though common fame long ſince ſaid that he intended ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to that purpoſe againſt Dr. <hi>Goddard,</hi> and my ſelf; and though this report was ſtrong, yet it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37550:5"/>
could never enter into my thoughts, he had the leaſt finger in a piece ſo illogical, and abſur'd both as to Matter and Language; whereby the Reader may plainly ſee how clearly and too honourably I vindicate him from being the Author of that Book, and upon what grounds and informations Mr. <hi>Stubbes</hi> raiſeth his reviling diſcourſes, and this I writ contrary to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſome perſons of quality and parts. Becauſe ſaid they <hi>he cares not what he writes againſt the R. S. and each member of it, and that the reviling Language well ſuited his uſual writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall take notice of ſome miſtakes (to ſpeak more gently) in his Pamphlet, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he intends to rear his Fabrick. In his Preface. <hi>In Oppoſition to Dr. Merret, I deduce the Original of the Apothecaries, from the times of Hippocrates and Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, through the Roman and Greek Empires,</hi> &amp;c. which he repeats in his Poſtſcript. In my view <hi>p.</hi> 27. I only ſpeak negatively of <hi>the Apothecaries antiquity in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>p.</hi> 28. I prove out of my <hi>Lord Cooke</hi> that <hi>K. Henry</hi> the ſixth had none. How impertinent then will his diſcourſe be, and quite beſides the purpoſe? (a practice much uſed by him in his writings.) How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I will be content he ſhall ſhew that he is well verſt in Lexicons and Indices, &amp;c. but ſhall mind him in that impertinent diſcourſe, that he fetcheth not their anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity as <hi>the Apothecaries</hi> ridiculouſly do from the Holy Scripture, wherein indeed the name of an <hi>Apothecary</hi> is four times found; but thoſe texts being examined, will carry no other ſenſe than of perfumers and makers of ſweet Ointments, trades to this day familiar in the Luxurious Eaſtern parts of the World. Secondly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37550:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Whether amongſt the Greeks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miraly ſignifie <hi>Poyſon,</hi> and ſecondarily, Spices, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and whether the word ſimply uſed was not taken in an ill ſenſe, and conſequently, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pharmacopaeus</hi> doth not properly ſignifie a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of Poyſons. Thirdly, In what good company, and for what good acts they are recorded in Authors, becauſe in <hi>Horace</hi> I find them ranked with the baſeſt of men, <hi>Ambubeiarum Collegia Pharmacopolae.</hi> I find alſo in <hi>Cicero, pro A. Cluentio,</hi> mention made of <hi>a Pharmacopola Circumforaneus, who in one night poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned a Citizens Wife of</hi> Rome, <hi>and ran away, but he was no Roman.</hi> But whereas you ſay that you will prove that there were in theſe elder times ſuch <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> as now there are (I do not mean Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, which by your promiſe you are obliged to do:) You will do ſomewhat, though little to the purpoſe, as I have ſaid, if you can prove, that they made and ſold Medicines in Shops before the time of <hi>Avicen,</hi> and were not perfectly Servants, and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing propoſed was, <hi>that the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> have a hand in all things written againſt the <hi>R. S.</hi> and in this Poſcript: As to the former, <hi>I am inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one that is of the Apothecaries Club, that all the Papers againſt the R. S. were ſent by Mr.</hi> Stubbe <hi>to this Club to have them Printed and diſperſt abroad, and that they ſent him intelligence:</hi> Beſides his bitter expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the R. S. in the Poſcript; moſt whereof is a Letter written to ſome of that company; where he ſaith, <hi>I adviſed them to reflect on our common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the R. S. and ſee if they were not the principal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries, and that I lookt upon it as a deſign of theirs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37550:6"/>
to aggrandize themſelves upon the ruine of the College, (a thing they have alwayes endeavoured) and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries.</hi> And p. 22. <hi>The Writings of the Virtuoſi have been the principal cauſe of all thoſe Controverſies, and which if they be not refuted, 'tis in vain to attack Medela Medicina, Manwaring,</hi> &amp;c. I have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed alſo by ſeveral other perſons of Credit, and worth, beyond any of this Junto, that <hi>F. B.</hi> an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary, and active againſt the <hi>R. S.</hi> and who long ſince vapoured he would anſwer my Book, ſhewed them <hi>H S.</hi> Manuſcripts againſt the <hi>R. S.</hi> and he, with his Brethren the Apothecaries, derided the <hi>R. S.</hi> talked over what Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> hath ſince publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and much more, in a ridiculous manner, to the great diſhonour of the Society, in their Clubs and Coffee Houſes, places where men talk any thing, and belye, and beſpatter whom they pleaſe, and ſurpriſe with falſities, and ridicule the ignorant and unwary. Now, whether thoſe Apothecaries were not the <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſons he mentions</hi> in his Preface to the Legend, <hi>he ſent to, to experiment their judgment, that his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parcels and fragments were joyned together with ſome alterations and new connexions, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of his at</hi> London; <hi>in fine, had not ſome publick ſpirited Gentlemen there undertook to tranſtate the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian pieces, and to ſee the work tranſcribed, and the inſertions made, and the connexion in ſome meaſure ſupplyed, I could never had leaſure to finiſh my intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> to which I add from the ſame Perſons, that ſeveral paſſages in <hi>H. S.</hi> Papers were blotted out, ſome added, other where interlinings, and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made. I ſay upon this paſſage, that 'tis very
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37550:6"/>
evident that this Club of Apothecaries, convey falſe Intelligence to <hi>H. S.</hi> and have correſpondence with him; and further, that they misinformed him of my entituling <hi>H. S.</hi> to be Author of <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> and were the cauſe of publiſhing this preſent Poſtcript at this unreaſonable time: Since he ſaith in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited place, <hi>The paſſages now Printed out of</hi> Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella <hi>were to follow his Vindication of</hi> Ariſtotle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (which hath not yet been made publick) <hi>and the breach that Piece hath made, in ſome other Papers, as he affirms in this Poſtcript.</hi> By which it appears the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries were the Authors or Adjutors in this ſcandalous Pamphlet. Add hereunto the many fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities alledged in theſe Papers, agreeable to what I often accuſe them elſewhere. And laſtly, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what power theſe Apothecaries, my implacable Adverſaries, have over his Papers, and what there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they have uſed I leave to indifferent Readers, whether the Apothecaries were the Contrivers, or Makers of this Libel againſt me; and if ſo, then the credit of it will of it ſelf fall to the ground, but if it came purely from <hi>H. S.</hi> 'twill find little repute from any learned, pious, or ſober Perſon. By all which it appears, that the ſaid Company is in perfect oppoſition to the <hi>R. S.</hi> As for my ſelf, I think no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man will deny, that the falſe news concerning my entituling Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> to <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> did give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to this Poſtcript, and did proceed from an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary,</hi> for who elſe could be ſo malicious as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him of ſo great an untruth without ſending him the Book? And how honeſtly Mr. <hi>Stubbes</hi> deals, in ſaying, he never ſaw that Book, ſince his Poſtcript
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37550:7"/>
wad dated from <hi>Ragley, June the 14th.</hi> ſeveral weeks after the publication of my Book, in which time he might have been eaſily informed of the falſity of his information in this particular.</p>
            <p>The next thing is, the unfair wayes they have in publiſhing their Papers againſt me: The Author of <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> was proved in my Anſwer to it to be a Libel without name of Author, Printer, or Licenſer. <hi>This great Goliah of the</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>hath ſo Printed his, that I can neither find Printer, Licencer, nor prove H. S. to be the Author of it,</hi> though his Name be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed to it; nor will the prime diſperſer of it, nor ſome of his correſpondents acknowledge him to be ſo.</p>
            <p>And thus having dealt with the Author as with <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> in firſt rehearſing his untruths, and then briefly refuting him; ſo having done with Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> as to the firſt part, I ſhall come to what is remaining in the Poſtſcript, and I ſhall ſpeak next to two heads, the one wherein we agree, the other wherein we ſeem to differ. I agree with him in this clauſe writ to the Apothecaries, in the following words, his own, <hi>That I could never invent or meet with any arguments that could induce me to allow of practicing Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and that I underſtood ſo well the extent, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of my Profeſſion, that however they might in ſome caſes proſper;</hi> and page 21. <hi>But I proteſted againſt any encouragement for Apothecaries to practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this alſo we are of the ſame mind, that there <hi>were many defaults needing regulation in them;</hi> moreover, <hi>that they (the Apothecaries) would not delude themſelves, that they could proſecute their Trades
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37550:7"/>
long; if that famed Body of men (the College of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians) did reſolve againſt them, with whoſe determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I did not doubt, but all intelligent Practicioners in the Countrey, and Counties, would comply:</hi> And elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he profeſſeth, <hi>He will write againſt the Divines, Mountebanks, Emperics, and Apothecaries, and ſuch idle Experimentators that practice Phyſic.</hi> As to the practice of Apothecaries, the whole drift, and all the arguments in my Book, as alſo thoſe other that have writ againſt them aime at that mark only, but Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> ſaith farther, <hi>He cannot invent, nor meet with any arguments for it,</hi> and doubtleſs would have written more bitterly then us all, if he had rightly conſidered the intereſt of the Profeſſion: Beſides, I wiſh that the Apothecaries might thrive and proſper as long as they keep themſelves within the Laws of reaſon, and of the Land, which are directly againſt their practice; I aſſert alſo that the College have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved againſt them, in Voting it honourable for their Members to make their Medicines. I ſay with him, and prove that <hi>there are many faults in them needing regulation,</hi> which defaults I have reduced to ſeveral heads, and enumerated them, and I think Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> will not countenance them in deſtroying and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring that famed Body of Men, the <hi>Corporation of Phyſicians,</hi> which I have fully proved they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes endeavoured to do by Overt Acts, as alſo the intolerable affronts, tricks, and devices they uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in their practice. I have acted alſo for many years together for what <hi>he hopes for</hi> in page 21. <hi>That Phyſicians would conſider their common intereſts, in oppoſition to the</hi> Thompſons and Odowds, <hi>&amp;c. and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37550:8"/>
act with that moderation which became wiſe men, and who were tender of continuing the renown of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, which would ſuddenly elſe devolve into the hands of Emperics, and demean themſelves with that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which might end in an accord with the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries.</hi> How I have acted in this Your hope, I ſhall briefly relate, and how I have proſecuted for many years together by the College Order: All the <hi>Trigs, Barkers, Odowds, &amp;c.</hi> and forced many Mountebanks from this City, and have publiſhed in Print, by their Order and for their Uſe, all that relates to their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, and whatſoever hath been diſputed in Law concerning their Rights, ſince their firſt foundation; ſo that things are now ſo well ſetled, that <hi>Emperics</hi> may be proſecuted without miſcarriages. I have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions awaited the College Councel, and ſpent much time with them upon their Charters and Law affairs; I have alſo ſpent many hours with the beſt of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> to compoſe all differences betwixt them and us, I have anſwered all their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, conſulted and endeavoured to ſecure them from their petty fears, and all pretended inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which might ariſe from our Charter to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; told them, <hi>The College would grant them what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they could in reaſon deſire, if they would confine themſelves to their Trades, and not uſurp on our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and I think none of them but will ſay how ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy I have entertained them at my Houſe, and with what moderation I have endeavoured to make an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord between them and us, but what prevarications, inconſtant reſolutions they uſed with me in this affair, I hope I ſhall have no occaſion farther to declare,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37550:8"/>
               <hi>and that my Book tended to the continuing the renown of my Faculty,</hi> I frequently ſay, and I think no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man can doubt thereof. Since therefore I have really and publickly acted what Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> owns (as is before recited) I wonder with what face he can ſay, <hi>He hath anſwered all in my Book,</hi> or this which followeth, <hi>As for Dr.</hi> Goddard <hi>who hath writ more warily and with greater prudence, I onely diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him in the Antiquity of Apothecaries, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him as a Phyſician, whom I pittyed for being mixt with ſo illiterate a company,</hi> which words imply Dr. <hi>Merret</hi> writ warily and prudently, for ſure every comparative muſt have its poſitive, beſides the ſame reaſons and almoſt all the ſame arguments are urged by us both againſt the Practicing <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and we concurr alſo in moſt of our arguments, for <hi>the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and uſefulneſs of Phyſicians making their own Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines;</hi> onely my Learned Collegue recites Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, the abuſes of <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> which every ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man may eaſily make affirmative, and <hi>that this is his wary way of writing. Beſides all the arguments and deſigns of us both, are to limit the</hi> Apothecaries <hi>in their Practice.</hi> Laſtly, we agree in this, <hi>That it was the intereſt of Phyſicians to emply Apothecaries as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Profeſſion, and that it was the prudence of States that it ſhould be ſo;</hi> all this I fully aſſent to, and ſay in my View, that it would ſave the Phyſician a great deal of money, time, and charges, which thoſe that make their own Medicines are neceſſarily put unto, ſuppoſing ſtill <hi>the Apothecaries kept themſelves within their bounds,</hi> as to Phyſicians, and made their Medicines honeſtly, and dealt juſtly in their Trade, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37550:9"/>
think but all Phyſicians will be of the ſame mind with me, if the Apothecaries fail in either or both, or act according to what I have ſaid in my View, ſo that if Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> makes this an univerſal propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, he muſt prove it lawful (which he denied before) <hi>That the Apothecary may practice Phyſic, and cheat the Cuſtomer;</hi> which certainly no State will allow.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for what we agree in. We ſeem, and perhaps but ſeem to differ onely in this which he affirms, <hi>p.</hi> 19. <q>That the reaſons to be alleged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Phyſicians preparing their own Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were ſuch as admitted of no Anſwer nor Evaſion among underſtanding men: and <hi>page</hi> 20. Upon this account I did largely handle that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether Phyſicians ought to make their own Medicines, which I reſolved in the Negative, and urged all thoſe arguments (with ſeveral illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) which have hitherto perſwaded with pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Governours and Phyſicians to eſtabliſh the received Uſage. And in his Preface to the Reader, I ſhew with what prudence both Phyſicians, and the civil Magiſtrates concurred to their Inſtitution, and I have largely entreated on that Queſtion, which the <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> in order to the ruine of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Phyſician, and of the Trade of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, to the great alteration of the practice of Phyſic, and aggrandizing of themſelves, have ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and with much confidence and more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance handled.</q> Which great brags and vapours of his, and his performances herein, will amount to juſt nothing if the Queſtion be ſtated as we put it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37550:9"/>
and it ought to be, for we ſay and prove that <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were eſtabliſhed in all Nations before the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries,</hi> and that <hi>Phyſicians did in all places firſt make their own Medicines by their own Servants;</hi> and that in proceſs of time by the Phyſicians connivance, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of buſineſs, and to ſave themſelves both trouble and charges, did permit and perhaps aſſiſt them (as hath been proved <hi>in England</hi> they did) to procure them liberty of the States, to make and compound Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines and that <hi>the Apothecaries are every where ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to the Phyſicians, and that the Phyſicians have been by no ſtate reſtrained from making their own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and have inſpection and correction over them;</hi> we farther prove that as affairs now ſtand betwixt <hi>the Phyſicians and Apothecaries in England,</hi> that they ought to make their own Medicines if they intend to ſupport their own Faculty and the honor of it, and to wipe of all thoſe falſe aſperſions unjuſtly caſt upon them by the <hi>Apothecaries of London:</hi> and that this is the only way to advance their skill in their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and in all Natural knowledg, as alſo the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unſufferable charges impoſed upon our Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents <hi>by the high Bills of the Apothecaries, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties of our ſucceſſes by reaſon of their detracting, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting, putting in falſe, decayed and unwholeſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients into our receipts, to the great diſcredit of our Faculty, and the unavoidable danger to the lives and healths of the Sick.</hi> I ſay this is the true ſtate of the preſent queſtion, and therefore all Mr. <hi>Stubbe's</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed anſwer and triumph before his reaſons alleged, will be as impertinent to the preſent buſineſs, as his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed diſcourſe concerning the Antiquitie of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37550:10"/>
for the queſtion is not as he propoſeth it, what arguments have ſwayed prudent Governours and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians to eſtabliſh the received uſage at ſuch times, I ſay when <hi>Apothecaries</hi> were bounded by the Laws and their own civility and intereſt, and where the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> were limited to a certain number from u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping our faculty: but whether as things now ſtand <hi>in England,</hi> we ought not (I think Mr. <hi>Stubbe</hi> will not ſay <hi>de Jure</hi> we ought not) in prudence, and for the publick good to make our own Medicines, for if he doth, <hi>I am ſure there are few of his mind, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of many in this City, and very many more in the Countrey, and many gratulatory Letters to me will, clearly evince the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I will conſider his advice given to <hi>the Apothecaries</hi> in his Letter to them, in theſe words; <hi>I did therefore earneſtly recommend unto their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion:</hi> Which recommendation whether the Apothecaries have followed or no by tendering the Committee of the College ſome propoſitions, and whether <hi>the project he ſaith is not difficult, and which he would not intimate that the College would joyn effectually therein,</hi> I ſay whether they were the effect of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter let every man judge, and whether inferiors ever offered their ſuperiors propoſitions with ſuch boldneſs, and incivility; for having diſputed amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about an hour, whether they ſhould deliver their proportions before the College delivered theirs to them, or whether both ſhould deliver them inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably (<hi>ſuch punctilios have Princes with Princes, Ambaſſadors with Ambaſſadors,</hi> viz. <hi>equals with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals</hi>) at laſt they did deliver theirs firſt, without
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37550:10"/>
either Title, or Date, rudely written, and interlined. Their propoſals or humble deſires were as they Phraiſe it. <hi>Firſt that the Phyſitians would not prepare, or compound Medicines as Apothecaries, to their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and ſecondly that they would not deprive them of their friends and acquaintance, by pretence of any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Arcanum, or otherwiſe. And then they humbly offer two things; Firſt, that the Phyſicians would not only joyn together with them in a frequent ſearch of all that keep Apothecaries ſhops, and Secondly, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of an Act of Parliament for the regulating of Phyſic, whereby to ſuppreſs all Empirics and illegal practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and makers of Phyſic, as common enemies to both.</hi> Now let the conſiderate Reader judge by reflexion on what I have collected from Mr. <hi>Stubbs,</hi> whether theſe are not the reſult of his project, Secondly how their humbly deſire, and humbly offer ſuits with their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about the manner of their delivery, and whether their implying of Phyſicians abilities to prepare and compound Medicine, Croſſeth not what they every where object againſt us, and for which they have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced us in Parliaments. And again whether they imply not by their frequent ſearch of Apothecaries Shops, the increaſing <hi>frauds of Apothecaries,</hi> becauſe they deſire that this ſearch may be frequent, having been formerly but once a year, and of late years none at all, and withall the abilities of Phyſicians for this ſearch, quite contrary to (their privately cryed up to unwary people, though diſowned by them to all underſtanding perſons) <hi>Lex Talionis, who ſaith in expreſs terms,</hi> p. 4. <hi>the Law might as well have ſet two Shoemakers as Cenſors, to be judges of the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37550:11"/>
Medicines, thoſe Cenſors for the moſt part not understanding the Tithe of the Medicines, and druggs in the Apothecaries ſhops, and</hi> p. 8. <hi>moſt of the Doctors not underſtanding the tithe of what is commonly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to paſs by their tautologie of <hi>Private Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> as much as to ſay red ſcarlet, <hi>or Apothecarie Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoeus;</hi> I will briefly conſider the abſurdity of the matter it ſelf. <hi>They deſire that Phyſicians will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and compound Medicines as Apothecaries to their prejudice;</hi> to which I ſay, we never intended to make them as <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> which <hi>I have ſhewed in my View to be done ſlovenly Fulſomely of unſound and unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſimples:</hi> But I ſuppoſe their meaning is, we ſhould not make them for our own Patients, and compound them, this being to their prejudice, though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much for our patients advantage, for without this preparing and compounding, I ſee not how our Art can make any Farther progreſs. For <hi>I have ſhewed in my view, that the want hereof hath been the cauſe our Art hath been at a ſtand, and gained no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs for ſome hundreds of years;</hi> beſides by this deſire they would have <hi>the College</hi> renounce their former vote, that it was honourable for their members ſo to do, and alſo to diveſt our ſelves of one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal parts of our faculty mainly relating to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of our Art, and immediately concerning the lives and healths of our Patients. Again if they mean <hi>the College</hi> ſhould tye their members from doing ſo, <hi>they deſire that which neither Law, common ſenſe, nor reaſon will allow</hi> and which they cannot do; as well may the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> deſire that <hi>Phyſitians</hi> would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37550:11"/>
not diſſect bodies themſelves, to their prejudice and ſo deprive themſelves of two main branches of their profeſſion <hi>Anatomy and Pharmacy.</hi> Beſides this word (to their prejudice) is of ſo large extent that it may be ſtretcht out to deny a Phyſician power to make Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for himſelf, Family and Relations, <hi>then which there's nothing more abſur'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond deſire is, <hi>that the Phyſitians will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of their friends and acquaintance by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of any private Arcanum, or otherwiſe.</hi> I am glad to ſee that my view hath wrought them out of one piece of nonſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the calling the ſick their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents; but yet obſerve how they Pride it above the reſt of <hi>the Citizens of London,</hi> of much better rank than themſelves, by diſdaining to call them Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</p>
            <p>As to the depriving them of their cuſtomers, I have treated largely in my Poſtſcript in anſwer to <hi>Lex Tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> and farther ſay that if the pretence of a private Arcanum were the onely cauſe thereof, I ſhould not wholy (all circumſtances rightly put) allow of it. But for their otherwiſe cloſeing up this (as to our preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice did the former) I have elſewhere proved by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons this deſire to be frivolous, and uncivil. <hi>For 'tis ſtrange if a Phyſician finds an Apothecary to be faulty in honesty or skill or both, or to act quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the preſcription of the Phyſician, or the Life and Health of the Patient, or that he hath not a good Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine in his ſhop, or that he endeavours to diſgrace the Phyſician and remove his Patient to a good Apothecaries Phyſician; that in theſe caſes, and in many other ſuch as theſe a Phyſician ſhould not deprive them of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37550:12"/>
Next <hi>they humbly offer that we would joyn with them in a frequent ſearch of the ſhops:</hi> this alone hath ſome pretence for the publick good, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality endeavors an advancing themſelves into an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality with <hi>the College.</hi> For whereas in <hi>the Act of Parliament</hi> the power is granted to <hi>the Phyſicians alone to deſtroy bad Medicines,</hi> and onely to take with them <hi>the Maſter and Wardens of the Apothecaries Company;</hi> Bur here they humbly offer <hi>that Phyſicians and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries may be joyned together, and be hail fellows well met.</hi> But if they refer this only to a frequent ſearch we are beholding to them for putting more trouble, charge, loſs of time and buſineſs upon us; it being impoſſible for us to act by others, as they do by their Servants. Beſides our Corporation never gained any thing by their ſearches, but troubles, and Suits of Law and the particular Cenſors revilings, for performing their duties according to their Oaths in deſtroying bad Medicines. But doubtleſs in a ſhort time the Cenſors will more effectually perform the truſt herein, and with more boldneſs and a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neglect of revilings, or other prejudices can ariſe to them from ſo doing. Nor is it to be expected that this ſearch will be performed as it ought to be, till the Company of the Apothecaris ſhall bid open defiance to our College, as they have, and do by clear conſequence, or till this ſearch ſhall be made by ſuch Cenſors as prepare their own Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>our conjunction with them for the procuring an Act of Parliament for the regulating of Phyſic.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Apothecaries mean not to be ſharers with us
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37550:12"/>
in this regulation, being a buſineſs beyond their Sphere and capacity, and only proper to our College, but if theſe words <hi>whereby to ſuppreſs all Empirics and illegal practicers and makers of Phyſic,</hi> &amp;c. explain the former, then I ſay we need no Act of Parliament for this: Nor in our late addreſſes to this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſired any ſuch power, and their Word illegal implies as much, and therefore 'twere fooliſh to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that we have already; Nay, as I have elſewhere proved, that practizing Apothecaries are illegal pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticers, by the expreſs Letters of our Charter, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirics, having noe lawful calling thereunto, but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they mean not ſo; ſo that all this ſeems to be but a blind to that which follows, <hi>viz. makers of Phyſic;</hi> this is the Alpha and Omega of their deſires, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha excludes Phyſicians onely, the Omega is Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, makers of Phyſic; which whether it extends to Surgeons who by the Apothecaries Charter are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make their own Medicines, and by all Lawes have right thereunto: and whom his Majeſty and the Merchants truſt before the Apothecaries to furniſh their Fleets and Ships, and alſo to Confectioners, Chymiſts, Diſtillers, to Ladies and Charitable perſons, that make Medicines for the poor and their families, &amp;c. I leave all thoſe that are concerned to judge, and the Apothecaries to explain, all this being to their prejudice, however this I ſay, it concerns not Phyſitians at all who make Medicines, but who pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice with them; neither have I heard of any Law in any Countrey forbidding perſons to make Medicines, nor I think will it ever be forbid: the Lawes onely provide who ſhall direct them, or who ſhall diſpenſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37550:13"/>
them in Shops. But how theſe makers of Medicines are prejudicial to both I underſtand not. I confeſs with their <hi>Hector H. S</hi> and their little <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> twill be mainly prejudicial to the Apothecaries, but 'till I underſtand by Phyſicians themſelves how it will be prejudicial to them, I ſhall ſay no further here, having proved it in my view to be to their great advantage: and ſhall onely add that theſe Overtures were highly reſented by the whole College at their meeting as in reaſon they ought to be.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole I ſhall remark two things. Firſt, that they endeavour to ingroſs and monopoliſe to themſelves all the power of making Medicines, and thereby depriving Phyſicians of what is eſſential to their profeſſion, and their very Birth-right, and to ſuffer one of their hands to be cut off in the acting part of their Faculty; and that in ſome things they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to gain a power equal to that of Phyſitians, but not a word to gain the only thing we want, an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to puniſh delinquents for ill practice, which will light moſt heavily on them if duly executed. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, obſerve that there is nothing in their deſire but what was prompted by their Patron <hi>H. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now probably conjecture at the reaſon of Mr. <hi>Stubbs</hi> beginning this quarrel. I underſtand by ſeveral perſons and alſo by ſome Letters of his written to a Noble perſon, that civil women about <hi>Warwick,</hi> will not adviſe with him, ſo that he muſt ſhortly leave that Town; add hereunto his reſtleſs nature and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſhiftings from place to place, no where ſetled nor quiet may induce him to repair to <hi>London,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of ſome practice from the Apothecaries, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37550:13"/>
that he uſeth ſeveral inſinuations to the College of Phyſicians, perhaps in hope to procure of them a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to practice there, which very wiſe men ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt he deſigns to do, the former is very probable, and that he might become a good Apothecaries Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician here, and that when he comes to Town he may have uſe of their Wives eſpecially <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> Urgente neceſſitate, and in the next Edition of his Book ſet <hi>H. S.</hi> after it inſtead of <hi>P. O.</hi> As for his deſign on the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege I ſuppoſe 'twill never take, for he tacitely grants (by his ſuppoſition and not confronting it) that heats and indignities had paſſed from the College to the Apothecaries. Beſides above 20 of their Society are members of the Royal Society alſo, <hi>all which H. S. calls Coxcombes, Illiterate, Impertinents, Comediants, Ignorants, Ridiculous,</hi> &amp;c. And more particularly that <hi>the number of Phyſicians in the R. S. will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to three underſtanding perſons,</hi> beſides elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he nameth <hi>but three perſons of the R. S. of any worth,</hi> whereof the learned Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> is one againſt whom when he was Library keeper he railed in moſt invective language; ſo that there he excludes all Phyſicians from learning or parts, and therefore 'twill be as ridiculous in him to addreſs himſelf to them as he doth to make the <hi>R. S. to addreſs themſelves to the Phyſicians.</hi> And now I come to the bottom of the Plot, betwixt him and the Apothecaries againſt my ſelf, as may appear by what hath been ſaid before; and this clauſe proves in the 22 page. <hi>The paſſage of Campanella being taken out thence, hath occaſioned that breach in it, which I have not now leaſure to redreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now why he ſhould maim that piece that he cannot
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37550:14"/>
redreſs, cannot appear to any fober man to have any other intendment, then to bring in his railing Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript ſtuft with ſo many falſities, and ſlanders; and if this common traducer had had any Sobriety, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or Religion: (neither of which all I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſt with ſay he hath a grain of) he would not have premiſed ſuch a Libel before his promiſed treatiſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now rehearſe what ignominy he throws upon me. <hi>I anſwer ſaith he all that Dr. Merrett had alleged, and ſhewed his intolerable ignorance in that Book, and if we might take an eſtimate of his parts from that writing, 'twas manifeſt he might better imploy his time in ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the method of Phyſic, then compoſing Medicaments, that after 30 years practice 'twas evident he underſtood not the rudiments of that Noble Science nor could ſtate a caſe therein.</hi> As to your anſwer of my Book it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by what I have ſaid a little before, that <hi>H. S.</hi> hath nothing to allege againſt Dr. <hi>Merrett;</hi> and <hi>for ſhewing his intolerable ignorance in that Book,</hi> I only ſay that I have diſcourſt it over with knowing perſons of all conditions, well skilled in all kinds of learning, the ableſt in my own Faculty; nay with the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries themſelves, yet never had the leaſt reflection of ignorance caſt upon it, a conſiderable part whereof conſiſts in matter of fact, known by all Phyſicians of this City of any eminence; and all objections made by the Apothecaries (as to matter of fact) clearly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in my Poſtſcript of the ſecond Edition, the reſt of the Books being clear undenyable, deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will free me from ignorance in it. But how well <hi>H. S.</hi> infers, is apparent by many other places of this Poſtſcript, <hi>p.</hi> 21. His words are theſe, <hi>the diſaſters
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37550:14"/>
of the late Dutchwars, the Plague, and Fire of London were leſs inconveniencies then the perpetuity of the R. S. that theſe Calamities admitted of ſome remedies here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but the evils they are likely to occaſion us will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be corrected by any humane prudence, and I doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether God would ſupport us by his providence, when they had debauched the Nation from all piety and honeſty, as well as civil wiſdome, H. S.</hi> every where pretends piety though he be proved in print to have preferred a little gain before his Religion, and ſaid to a perſon of honour, it was not half a crown diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in what Religion he bred his Children, and for his Morality how he hath debauched ſome younger perſons, 'tis too long for me to recite. Beſides his inference out of <hi>Campanella</hi> that the R. S. are bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Popery, is ſo abſur'd that no freſh man of the Univerſity would own for fear of being rediculous. But to inferr ſuch a concluſion out of my Book, which hath neither a caſe ſtated, nor a word of the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Phyſic, plainly proves his extream malice and the exceeding weakneſs of his judgment. But <hi>H. S.</hi> goes on <hi>and if we might take an eſtimate of his parts from that writing.</hi> If <hi>H. S.</hi> had pleaſed, or doth read Books of real learning and that on ſeveral ſubjects, he might have taken notice that my labours have ſome eſteem with the learned pens of this age, and would have made another eſtimate of my parts, and that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors can compoſe medicaments better then the whole Companie of Apothecaries; his offer not accepted of by them doth clearly evince, and hath been thought by his contemporaries, and colleguesto have not only ſtudied, but fully underſtood the method of Phyſic,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37550:15"/>
and that above 30 years ago he underſtood the rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Noble Science, and could ſtate a caſe therein, or elſe the Univerſities are to be blamed for admitting of him to his degrees, and hereby our College alſo is highly accuſed and ſlander'd for admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one thus ignorant 20 years ago; much more to have choſen him for ſo many years to be one of their Cenſors, and to read a Public Anatomy Lecture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them 15 years ſince: in which he had ſome opportunity to ſhew his skill in both, and I may mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly ſay thoſe Pathological Lectures found ſome applauſe, as both the College Regiſter, and ſeveral importunities for the Printing of them make manifeſt, and perhaps the publication of them ſhall declare. Add hereunto that the immortal Dr. <hi>Harvey</hi> was to blame in nominating with ſome Eulogy ſuch a pitiful Phyſician to be his Library keeper, who neceſſarily was to converſe with learned forreiners and travailers in the Art of Phyſic. Laſtly my converſation hath been, and frequent conſultations with ableſt of my profeſſion. But I am too large on this ſubject, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially finding two worthy Divines Dr. <hi>Sprat</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> traduced in their own profeſſion by this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (whoſe mouth nothing leſs then a Serjeant can ſtop.) <hi>His words of them are theſe, p. 22. Whoſe abilities in matters relating to their profeſſion are ſo contemptible that 'twere folly,</hi> &amp;c. But this detraction cannot much prejudice theſe Divines as being fixt in their employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but his abominable ſcandal cunningly driven on by the Apothecaries, may do me; and for which end only this Poſtſcript was writ who Candeſtinely may uſe this ſlight to my diſadvantage to tell ignorant people
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37550:15"/>
not verſt in men nor books, or to ſuch who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagators of falſe news, that Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> hath been prov'd in Print, and that by a very learned writer, not to underſtand the very rudiments of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic, and to add more what their malice can invent, and doubtleſs this was the ſole reaſon of contriving and unſeaſonably publiſhing this Libel, as all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may evidence to underſtanding men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. Since this Pamphlet was in the Preſs, I Received a note incloſed in a Letter from Mr. <hi>John Starkey</hi> a Book-ſeller near <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of <hi>H. S' s.</hi> Poſtſcript, who denyed not to me nor my Servant, that it came from the ſaid <hi>H. S.</hi> The words ſent me by ſaid Mr. <hi>Starkey</hi> were theſe. <hi>When you ſee him next you may tell him. That if he pleaſe know the ground of the ſuppoſition, 'tis the caſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary, giving a ſtrong purge before the fit of a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, mentioned in his Book. He hath neither given us an account of the habit of the patients body, the time of the year, the Type and time of the quartan, whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or inveterate with or without ſigns of connextion,</hi> (I ſuppoſe it ſhould be concoction) <hi>nor of the Purge it ſelf, nor how long miniſtred before the fit, all which are requiſite to the true ſtate of a caſe, as every Phyſician knows, and yet would have us condemn the Apothecary, for doing that which (whatever the event may have been) for ought I can ſee, no underſtanding Phyſician can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, as I ſhall demonſtrate out of a multitude of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Phyſicians; ſo that if we may judge by that caſe no man can make any other collection.</hi> Before I animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert on this paſſage, I ſhall recite it as 'tis in my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37550:16"/>
view, <hi>p.</hi> 45 of the firſt, and <hi>p.</hi> 62 of the ſecond Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; 'tis in theſe words. As for their skill in practice we daily ſee their groſs errours and omiſſions, (which I now add ſome Phyſicians and in Print too call mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) being cal'd where they have given Medicines. I ſhall inſtance onely in one that hapned at the writing hereof, <hi>viz.</hi> that an Apothecary gave ſtrong purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pils on the fit day of a gentle quartan Ague, which turned it into a violent Fever, to the great hazard of the Patients life. Obſerve firſt, how fairly <hi>H. S.</hi> cites me, I ſay ſtrong purging pills, <hi>H. S. a ſtrong purge;</hi> juſt as <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> I ſay on the fit day of a gentle quartan Ague, <hi>H. S. before the fit of a quartan.</hi> For this his miſreciting of my words may much vary them and alter much my ſenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> take notice of his intolerable ignorance (to uſe his own words) in ſaying the type of a quartan. For type is joyned with a Fever in general, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the ſpecies of Fevers into Quotidian, Tertian, Quartan. And when a Phyſician asketh what type a Fever hath, the Anſwer a Quotidian, double Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, &amp;c. Becauſe type is as Galen, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (i. e.) <hi>the order of intention and remiſſion.</hi> So that I might hence conclude and deſervedly too, that <hi>H. S.</hi> underſtands not the Terms, and conſequently not the very Rudiments of that noble Science he ſeems ſo much concerned for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> obſerve his Logic. He ſaith I have neither given an account of the habit of the Patient, &amp;c. and thence concludes that Dr. <hi>Merret</hi> underſtands not the Rudiments of Phyſic, nor can ſtate a caſe therein, <hi>H. S' s</hi> Logic right, and ſuch as is uſed at <hi>Billings-gate.</hi> I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37550:16"/>
do not ſtate this caſe in my Book, and therefore he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers can ſtate none at all, excellent reaſoning. Any man may better Collect from Mr. <hi>Stubbes</hi> his <hi>plus ultra p. 148. that he cauſed himſelf to bleed october 20 being not well at Warwick, by reaſon of a violent defluxion into the glandules of the throat,</hi> that he knows not how to put a caſe in Phyſic, becauſe he doth not ſet it down with all the circumſtances belonging to the diſeaſe it ſelf. And <hi>ib. 138. Amongſt other preparatives to the Bath I cauſed my ſelf to be let blood for my health.</hi> But to conclude, <hi>H. S.</hi> underſtands cannot put a caſe in Phyſic, becauſe he doth not fully ſtate the two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſes I judge to be very hard, and leſs to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to demonſtrate out of a multitude of Eminent Phyſicians the badneſs of his practice in both caſes, which is eaſy enough to do in his way. Certainly no man but would think this inference to be more concluding that <hi>H. S. is a ſubverter of the Monarchy of England, and of the repute of the Clergy,</hi> becauſe he ſaith in his Preface to the Hiſtory of the R. S. <hi>there were times wherein he thought it our intereſt to do both.</hi> But then ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (but not granting) the caſe had been ſtated (as 'twas not by his own confeſſion) and Stated too amiſs; Certainly from one particular to reaſon univerſally to a whole Science is moſt bruitiſh. I think <hi>H. S.</hi> would judge ſo if a man ſhould conclude by his rendition of good nature in Engliſh by <hi>un homme de bonne nature, &amp; l'homme d'un box naturel,</hi> in French, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies no more then a man of good natural parts, or of his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Greek or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I ſay if a man ſhould conclude by <hi>H. S.</hi> miſtake in this ſaid caſe that he underſtands neither French nor Greek and is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37550:17"/>
no Critic, I ſhould confeſs ſuch a concluder to be a fooliſh and malitious adverſary to him. And who would not laugh at a perſon that ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Smith or other Tradeſman to be wholy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in his whole Trade and every part thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he miſtakes in putting one caſe in his Art. But I trifle as well as he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> His inference ſeems by himſelf to be far fetched, and unknown to me (as indeed it was) or elſe why ſhould he ſay to his correſpondent? <hi>if he</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf.) <hi>pleaſe to know the ground of the ſuppoſition, 'its the caſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I anſwer the nature of my Book required not the putting down the caſe and all the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereunto belonging. And 'twould have been judged abſur'd in a treatiſe of that nature to have put a caſe of practice underſtood only by Phyſicians. If the Apothecary complain'd of, had found himſelf aggreived, and had urged it, then indeed to have put the caſe fully might have been expected, but not otherwiſe. But if <hi>H. S.</hi> will arraign every Phyſician, as he doth me, for accuſing Apothecaries (who are Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rics) of ill practice, without putting the caſe home, few Phyſicians would avoid this cenſure of intollerable ignorance. Nay if Mr. <hi>Stubbes</hi> or any other had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to have had the caſe put, I ſhould not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to have done it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> whereas <hi>H. S.</hi> requires an account of many things, I ſay, when I put that caſe to a Phyſician I ſhall add ſeveral material things (whereof he ſeems ignorant) to put it full, and as it ought to be.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:37550:17"/>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> I ſay Phyſicians daily do, and lawfully may ſpeak in general, that ſuch a man was kil'd by ſuch an Apothecary, by not letting him blood, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Opiat, Vomit, or Purge in ſuch a diſeaſe, without relating all the circumſtances of it; and though ſome ignorant people may judge him mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious for ſaying ſo: yet neither Phyſician nor theſe ignorants will traduce him for ignorance in that caſe, much leſs in his whole Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly, H. S.</hi> concludes Dr. <hi>Merrett would have us condemn the Apothecary for doing that which</hi> (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the want were) <hi>for ought I can ſee, no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Phyſician can condemn, as I ſhall demonſtrate out of a multitude of Phyſicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I reply that all civil men of the faculty would have thought a Fellow of the College of Phyſicians affirmation had been ſufficient enough againſt a practiſing Apothecary, without putting the caſe at all; and examples enough may be ſhown Phyſicians ſo doing. And though I reſt not wholy on the event with the vulgar, which I have ſufficiently confuted elſewhere, yet to make a judgment on ill ſucceſs from bad practice is rational. <hi>H. S.</hi> proceeds, <hi>for ought I can ſee</hi> (modeſtly ſaid.) Why he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth he knows nothing of the Caſe, neither the habit of the Patient, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> and therefore he is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate out of a multitude of Eminent Phyſicians, that 'tis lawful to give ſtrong purging Pills on the fit day of a gentle quartan, let the circumſtances and ſymptoms of the diſeaſe, and the condition of the Patient be what they will, or elſe <hi>H. S.</hi> oppoſeth not at all what the view affirmeth; and he here
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37550:18"/>
puts himſelf on as wild a task as <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> who would prove out of Hippocr. that the old Medicines were better then mine. The Reader may plainly fee, that <hi>H. S.</hi> undertakes to confute a Story he knows nothing of, and to demonſtrate out of Authors, he knows not what himſelf: And ſo let <hi>H. S.</hi> paſs with his third impertinence not yet Printed, for I am weary with this pitiful ſtuff.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. S.</hi> in the ſaid note appeals to ſome of our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and permits me to choſe whom I pleaſe to be as judges in the caſe. Bravely ſaid, were <hi>H. S.</hi> in <hi>London</hi> he would ſoon find the Cenſors of the College, and the whole body ſevere judges againſt him, and that this young Phyſician at <hi>Warwic</hi> were impudent to appeal to them in ſo notorious a ſcandal, beſides the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, not the accuſer appeals; and too be ſure their ſentence would be againſt him, not only for ſo bruitiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traducing one of their members, (their ſtatute of civil converſation where of <hi>H. S.</hi> hath none requiring the contrary to what he acts) but alſo for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſo their fellows, and his promiſed Support of them would make them (as it doth) very good ſport.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. S.</hi> concludes his letter to the Apothecaries thus, <hi>p. 22. This was the ſubject of that Book, which I doubt not but will be approved by all judicious perſons; and the College will ſee I can write againſt Dr.</hi> Merret, <hi>without derogating from them; or rather that my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments were to SUPPORT them and not diſſerve the APOTHECARIES in the leaſt. I intend to make it public in Michaelmaſs term.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37550:18"/>I ſhall make a ſhort commentary on this Epiphone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma of <hi>H. S.</hi> ſetting out his confidence of judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons approving this Book, which ſober men would have left to the Cenſure, and opinion of the Readers; and not have ſo long before hand triumphed and ſung the praiſes on his own undertakings. Of which I ſhall ſay in general what the moſt learned, and indifferent perſons judge of his writings, that they are wholy void of judgment, reaſon and Logic, and conſiſt only of railings, impertinent readings, and contain little but Pedantic learning, Antiquity and Grammar, of little uſe to ſuch as write of things. But to the particulars. <hi>This was the ſubject of that Book.</hi> And was this all? The Title page mentions a Poſtſcript concerning the quarrel depending be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>H. S.</hi> and Dr. Merret, and yet the Poſtſcript its ſelf hath the leaſt part of this quarrel. The greater part whereof directly oppoſeth the <hi>R. S.</hi> onely, much of it relates to the College and Apothecaries, ſomething to Dr. <hi>Goddard</hi> and not much to my ſelf beſides the falſity in the beginning, ſo that the whole Poſtſcript ſeems to be written onely to defame me: ſo well doth the Title and Poſtſcript anſwer one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Beſides this, you will doubtleſs run an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Riſco for the old Medicines, and againſt the new diſcoveries in your Pedantic way, and no man knowes whether <hi>H. S.</hi> goes on. <hi>I doubt not this Book will be approved by all judicious perſons.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcarcely by any, not by the learned perſons the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> you ſent your Papers to, to experiment them, &amp;c. For you reſtrain them from practiſe, tell them many things needed regulation in them, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37550:19"/>
the College reſolving againſt them would deſtroy their trade; that you in your intendments were to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the College; you rank them in the loweſt place of Emperics and Quackſalvers. Certainly none of theſe things will the Apothecaries approve, nor Phyſicians neither; you oppoſe their vote, that 'tis honourable for their members to make their own Medicines: you ſuppoſe that indignities and heats had paſſed from the College toward the Apothecaries, you recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the Apothecaries an union with the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and as they apply it to make them our Peers, you ſay of 20 of their Society members alſo of the R. S., that they are Coxcombs, Impertinents, &amp;c. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. You here proudly take upon you to be their ſupport as if they were not able, or willing to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelves, but an extraneous perſon ignorant of their affairs, ſo infamous and notorious muſt do it for them, you would deprive all Phyſicians of their Eſſential privilege, nay which is common for all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to do, <hi>viz.</hi> making their own Medicaments, you call ſome of the Fellows of the College princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal incendaries. And therefore you may very well doubt whether Phyſicians really ſo, and who are the moſt proper judges of this matter will approve your Book at all, I am ſure none I have converſed with, will in the leaſt, you profeſs your ſelf an implacable adverſary to the R. S. threaten each Virtuoſi there, and ſurely not one member of that illuſtrious body will approve your Book.</p>
            <p>As for Divines you have written againſt them in general and endeavoured to diſtroy their very order, and particularly againſt the learned Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37550:19"/>
               <hi>Sprat,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glanvil,</hi> and ſay of the two latter, 'twere folly to expect much from them where they profeſs; and if they diſpleaſe you, you will ſay of all of them as you do of the two latter, that their abilities in matters relating to their profeſſion are contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible.</p>
            <p>As for Gentlemen of the long Robe, and all perſons Loyal to the King, few of them either read or value your writings, and ſeveral of theſe are members of the R. S. alſo. And on good grounds think you would act over again your former diſloyalties.</p>
            <p>And if none of the three profeſſions will approve of your Book, then certainly neither will either of the Univerſities, as neither do they diſapprove of Dr. <hi>Merretts</hi> view, I am ſure many forreigners <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> beſides judicious perſons of all orders have given the Author thanks for it; and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as have found double advantage by it, as well to their healths as purſes.</p>
            <p>Beſides 'tis ſtrange this Phyſician at <hi>Warwic</hi> ſhould conceive ſo well of his Book, founded wholy either on falſities or impertinencies, as hath been proved, and alſo on defamations ſo groſs, and deductions ſo abſurd and ridiculous as hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. S.</hi> proceeds. <hi>And the College will ſee that I can write against Dr. Merrett, without derogating from them; or rather that my intendments were to S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PORT them, and not diſſerve the Apothecaries in the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſind <hi>H. S.</hi> performing ſome wonders, firſt he can write againſt Dr. <hi>Merrett,</hi> and not dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the College, if he means he can rail at,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37550:20"/>
and miſrepreſent Dr. <hi>Merrett,</hi> and not in expreſs terms the College, perhaps H. S. can out of his rich maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of both perform his promiſe. But doubtleſs the College cannot conceive but that the writing againſt one or more of their members will derogate from them, eſpecially acting but their duties according to their faith given, and aſſerting their Honours, Rights, Privileges, Statutes, and Votes, and ſpeaking their own private Language and Diſcourſes. And ſurely no man can judge otherwiſe then that Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> in his Book intended the good and wellfare of the College, and hath induſtriouſly proſecuted that end before his own profit, and undergone all tasks though never ſo ungratefull in order thereunto. How then <hi>H. S.</hi> can write againſt Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> and not dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the College, I think none of them can ſee. And farther <hi>H. S.</hi> will be hard put to it, to bring one inſtance to prove any Corporation ever thought themſelves not derogated from, when one of their members, hath been traduced for aſſerting their rights. And <hi>H. S.</hi> if diſpleaſed, will then call them the College of inſenſaty for ſo doing, as he doth the R. S. and conſequently a conſequently a conſiderable number of them allready.</p>
            <p>But here he not only profeſſeth he will not dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from them, (a great kindneſs in him towards learned men, though in many places he hath dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and decried many of them) <hi>but rather</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that my intendments were to ſupport them (the College) and not diſſerve the Apothecaries in the leaſt.</hi> Behold here the intendments of this man of might, doing wonders if not impoſſibilities. He intends to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37550:20"/>
do more then the eſtabliſhed Lawes and Charters, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Council board, proclamations of the King; judgments of Courts, the underſtanding labour induſtry and expences of the College, and all their intereſt ever could effect. Behold here this Hoghen Moghen PATRON and SUPPORT of the College, nay which is more for all this <hi>hee will not diſſerve the Apothecaries in the leaſt.</hi> He can blow in one breath hot and cold, he can ſupport the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and reſerve to them alone the practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic (which is all the ſupport they crave) and yet not diſſerve the Apothecaries in the leaſt, whoſe onely aim and indeavour is, and hath been to ſupplant and depreciate the Phyſicians; whereby to gain all the practice into their own hands, and without which (they ſay) they cannot gain a lively-hood.</p>
            <p>So that if <hi>H. S.</hi> take from them the practice of Phyſic (which he twice doth in this Poſtſcript) he doth them the greateſt diſſervice imaginable; but if he means to ſupport the College, he muſt take out of their hands the practical part of our faculty, and ſo conſequently (as the Apothecaries confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) undo them, and certainly this is not to diſſerve them in the leaſt, but in the whole. So that (as matters now ſtand) 'tis impoſſible to ſupport the one, but he muſt diſſerve the other. And if his project (he ſaith is not difficult) can ſecure the Phyſicians in their practice from the uſurpation of the Apothecaries, and not do the latter diſſervice (the ſole intendment and end of our Books) we ſhall confeſs him the only ſeeing perſon, and that he ſeeth more at a diſtance then we do upon the place, and ſhall for working
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37550:21"/>
this admirable and incredible wonder both admire and thank him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the ſupport of Phyſicians implies the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them from the frauds and abuſes committed in remedies, and the chargeableneſs of their Bills, the removing whereof (a thing impoſſible) muſt needs be diſſervice at leaſt to the Apothecaries, and he is bound to make good and juſtifie, or deny all thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints mentioned in my view, or elſe he doth diſſerve them. But perhaps he means by not diſſerve them, he will do them no harm in the leaſt, though poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively he will not ſerve them in the leaſt, and then they are but a little beholding to him, unleſs he will ſay that two negatives <hi>not</hi> and <hi>dis</hi> make an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative and ſo reſerve to himſelf by this ambiguous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion a power of doing them no prejudice, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them real ſervice if occaſion, and his advantage prompt him to it.</p>
            <p>Now here I ſhall make a very ſhort Apology for ſpeaking and treating ſo harſhly and perſonally (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my genius and reply to <hi>LexTalionis</hi>) the Author of this Poſtſcript; had he not malitiouſly, conſpiring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and upon no provocation given, nor upon any grounds raiſed ſuch a defamation upon me in my own profeſſion, I ſhould not have made the leaſt reflection upon him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe many ignorant and vain perſons underſtand not, or at leaſt take little or no notice of what is ſubſtantial; 'twas but juſt to take off by this way the ſcandal deſignedly caſt upon me, and to invalidate his concluſion, as Lawyers do the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their adverſaries by a lawfull recrimination.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37550:21"/>
Neither have I ſaid more then was neceſſary for my own defence. The reſt, and what I have ſaid will ſhortly be made publick concerning his life, and more fully, and if I am not miſinformed, will render him the moſt notoriouſly ill natured, as well as ill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered man in this Nation; eſpecially in one that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to learning, and who hath had Univerſity edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. He hath his hand againſt every man, and therefore cannot in reaſon but expect that every mans hand will be againſt him. And did I not confine my ſelf to his Poſtſcript, I could ſhew multitude of abſurdities, impertinences, falſities, weak inferences wanton expreſſions, and miſtakes of his in ſome other writings of his, I have read ſince the publication of his <hi>Campanella,</hi> and this Poſtſcript. All which I doubt not but Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> will effectually and ſhortly perform. And now I leave him to make publick what he pleaſeth at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term, when he is like to have other Irons in the fire. Beſides he may now perceive by a third Author, a worthy member of our College and of the R. S. alſo, who this day publiſhed ſome papers writ in the year 1664. at the requeſt of ſeveral Fellows of the College of Phyſicians, that many of us now have, and have had the ſame thoughts touching the practice of Phyſic in England, and invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Art by Apothecaries; and that they are more dangerous Enemies to our practice then all the others you mention Divines, Quacks, and Mountebanks, &amp;c. I have ſeen ſeveral other treatiſes on the ſame ſubject, which in time may come abroad too, writ long ſince by thoſe which are not members of the R. S. but of our College onely; ſo that he will have work enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37550:22"/>
from the College, and that this writing againſt me, is written at leaſt againſt many of the College, and thoſe not the meaneſt of that Corporation, or famed body of men.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>H S.</hi> doth in his laſt page ſo confound things and perſons, that I cannot tell to whom ſome paſſages relate: Yet 'tis manifeſt what ever he faith throughout, hath reference to the Virtuoſi; and that therefore I may give full anſwer to all his Poſtſcript: I ſhall take notice of two things, in the one he ſaith <hi>their Medicines are deluſory, and their new diſcoveries we very well knew before.</hi> But this is ſaid moſt inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and blindly, (in his own Language) for how can any man know or judge of thoſe Medicines made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately by a ſingle perſon, that they are deluſory or were known before. When 'tis ſcarcely poſſible any man can know any of the ingredients themſelves, much leſs of the preparing and compounding them. And how can <hi>H. S.</hi> tell who have or have not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant with the practice of the moſt eminent Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, or read their Books, when they intend not to tell him what their new diſcoveries are?</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond where he affirms, <hi>Ordinary prudence would have foreſeen the iſſue of thoſe kinds of writings.</hi> I ſpeak thus in my view, knowing that hereby a whole Company of men, (who by their number, noice, and tricks) may be able to decry and Phyſician, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my implacable adverſaries, &amp;c. but not fearing the utmoſt their malice can invent or proclaim, &amp;c. This I expreſly foreſaw, that the Apothecaries were not able to anſwer the Book, unleſs by the railing pen of a <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> which <hi>H. S.</hi> himſelf diſlikes, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37550:22"/>
'twas eaſy alſo for me to ſee that the Apothecaries would procure ſome mercinary pen to act their part of falſities and railings, and that you were the onely perſon likely to perform this task for them, all this I ſay I foreſaw and foretold, and much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe writings; as well as I did foretel in print the Fall of your Patron, under the name of <hi>Hen. Vanus,</hi> when he was in the prime of his proſperity, a conſiderable time before the Kings return. You con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <hi>with a performance too great for the Merretts and the Sydenhams,</hi> and never ſay, what this performance is? what you mean by the <hi>Sydenhams</hi> I know not, but this I may modeſtly ſay, that the <hi>Merretts</hi> can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form as much as the <hi>H S' ss.</hi> or the <hi>Talion aſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve Reader I will not any more be diverted by the Pens of either of them, or their accomplices; all whoſe notorious and illiterate malice, their forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and falſities or impertinent anſwers: I ſhall here after paſs over without any other reply, then that of a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſilence, as <hi>H. S.</hi> phraiſeth it; permitting him or them to ramble up and down in their impertinencies, and pretended anſwers, as he doth to the <hi>Plus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra,</hi> and the Hiſtory of the R. S. cavelling onely at ſome few paſſages in a large Book; and ſometimes ſetting up himfelf a man of clouts, and ſo fighting with it, and that is all you are to expect of him at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term againſt Dr. <hi>Goddard</hi> and my ſelf. One thing I had almoſt forgot to mention, wherein perhaps he might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault my Book, not ſpoken of in his Poſtſcript; but in his <hi>plus ultra, viz.</hi> his commendation of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Medicines, for this time let the Learned <hi>Zwelfer</hi> often commended by himſelf anſwer for me, and when
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37550:23"/>
he hath anſwered him (which is impoſſible to be done) I ſhall in few ſheets of paper make ſome Additions to what <hi>Zwelfer</hi> hath ſaid on that Argument; and for the future ſhall think it no diſiepute to be detracted from by this Phyſician at <hi>Warwic,</hi> who hath endeavoured to diminiſh my moſt honoured friends, the ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Dr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Boyl,</hi> Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lower,</hi> and the inquiſitive ſober and diſcreet perſons Mr. <hi>Henſhaw,</hi> Mr. <hi>Evelyn,</hi> &amp;c. and many other Famous men of our Nation: And ſhall conclude with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to the Apothecaries, that 'tis convenient for them to vindicate their reputation from the baſe titles of Wittals and Cuckolds caſt upon their Company, and to vindicate the College alſo from the ſlanders of their <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> and to give him juſt puniſhment and that they may have ſome ground for their ſearch, I ſhall give them ſome directions to find him out; my information was by a perſon of Quality well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his hand writing, who ſaw his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Printing of it; and hath often heard him ſpeak the ſame Language compriſed in that Book: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the merry and feigned ſtories in it, if this be ſufficient light for them to ground their diſcovery on, he is a Brother Apothecary, and ſhall be named unto them, if the Company deſire it by their Maſter and Wardens.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37550:23"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>DESIRETH the Reader to read in my view <hi>pag. 48. l. 17.</hi> Silver-ſmith, and acquaints him (that ſince there's no end of Libelling) he is to expect from me no more on this ſubject, unleſs the Company of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries or any other perſon or perſons for them ſhall write upon the whole or any part of the view; and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in writing under his, or their hands, objections or anſwers to ſome third perſon of known integrity, who ſhall ſoon receive Dr. <hi>Merretts</hi> anſwer thereunto, and ſhall publiſh all together, and both parties conform to his inſtructions in the managery of this controverſie, ſo that ſome end may be put thereunto. Which is the only fair way can in my opinion be taken in this affair.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 14th 1670.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:37550:24"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>r.</hi> propoſitions, <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>r.</hi> importunings; <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> underſtands not and <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> the event, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> whither <hi>H. S. p.</hi> 36. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> inſenſati.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
